Guide to the Department of University Health, Division of Student Mental Hygiene, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- General Files and Correspondence, 1926-1964; Series II
  - Presidents of Yale [Seymour, Charles, and Griswold, Alfred Whitney], 1949-1951 (Box 14, Folder 113)
  - Princeton University, 1929-1930 (Box 14, Folder 114)
  - "Professional Schools and Mental Health," [report by Lawrence K. Frank], 1950 (Box 14, Folder 115)
  - Proposal for creating "American Association of School and College Psychiatrists", 1935 (Box 14, Folder 116)
  - Provost's office, 1943-1953 (Box 14, Folder 117)
  - Psychiatrists recommended, by city, [ca. 1953] (Box 14, Folder 118)
  - Psychiatry and religion, 1948 (Box 14, Folder 119)
  - Q [general], 1937-1949 (Box 15, Folder 120)
  - R [general], 1927-1949 (Box 15, Folder 121)
  - Rademacher, Everett, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 122)
  - Raymond, Alice F., 1944-1947 (Box 15, Folder 123)
    See also: Series III. Project Files, 1929-1956
  - Requests for advice [from other colleges], 1927-1929 (Box 15, Folder 124)
  - Research Council on Human Reproduction, 1941 (Box 15, Folder 125)
  - "Retrospect and Prospect: A Special Report on the Twenty-fifth Anniversary of the Student Mental Hygiene Service at Yale," by Clements C. Fry and Edna G. Rostow
    - Manuscript, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 126)
    - Comments on, 1951-1952 (Box 15, Folder 127)
  - Robinson, Harvey A., 1946-1950 (Box 15, Folder 128)
  - Roblyer, William A., 1948-1951 (Box 15, Folder 129)
  - Ruggles, Arthur H., 1927-1955 (Box 15, Folder 130 - 131)
    See also: Series III. Project Files, 1929-1956 Folder 46
  - S [general], 1926-1949 (Box 15, Folder 132)
  - Schizophrenia, 1939-1949 (Box 15, Folder 133)
  - Sexual psychopath, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 134)
  - Shor, Joel, 1946-1949 (Box 15, Folder 135)
  - Social work, 1930 (Box 15, Folder 136)
  - Social Work Conference, 1931 (Box 16, Folder 137 - 138)
  - Sonneman, Ulrich, 1946 (Box 16, Folder 139)
  - Southbury Training School, 1939-1942 (Box 16, Folder 140)
  - Spottswood, Maurice, 1946 (Box 16, Folder 141)
  - Staff meetings, 1950-1957 (Box 16, Folder 142)
  - Student Health Service annual reports, 1947-1952 (Box 16, Folder 143)
  - Suggestions from other university departments, 1947-1949 (Box 16, Folder 144)
  - Summer course, 1949 (Box 16, Folder 145)
  - T [general], 1929-1949 (Box 16, Folder 146)
  - Thompson, Lloyd J., 1927-1930 (Box 16, Folder 147)
  - Thorne, Lewis
    - While away, 1943-1950 (Box 16, Folder 148)
    - After death, 1950-1954 (Box 16, Folder 149)
    - Memorial library at Timothy Dwight College, 1951-1952 (Box 16, Folder 150)
  - Torre, Mottram P., 1949-1950 (Box 16, Folder 151)
  - U [general], 1944-1948 (Box 16, Folder 152)
  - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc., 1949-1950 (Box 17, Folder 153)
  - University News Bureau, 1944-1951 (Box 17, Folder 154)
  - V [general], 1935-1948 (Box 17, Folder 155)
  - W [general], 1927-1949 (Box 17, Folder 156)
  - "What makes a good athletic trainer?" [report by O'Donnell and Robinson], undated (Box 17, Folder 157)
  - White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, 1931 (Box 17, Folder 158)
  - Winternitz, Milton C., 1943-1955 (Box 17, Folder 159)
  - Withers, Carl, 1947-1949 (Box 17, Folder 160)
  - World Federation for Mental Health
    - Agendas and planning materials, 1949 (Box 17, Folder 161)
    - Specialist Committee on Student Mental Health, 1954-1955 (Box 17, Folder 162)
    - Material used by Fry at conferences, 1949 (Box 17, Folder 163)
  - World Health Organization, 1946-1954 (Box 17, Folder 164)
  - Y-Z [general], 1931-1949 (Box 17, Folder 165)
  - Yakovlev, Paul I., 1949 (Box 17, Folder 166)
  - "Yale as seen by 22 Undergraduates," [report by by C. S. Ford], 1946-1947 (Box 17, Folder 167)
  - Yale College, Executive Committee, 1946-1947 (Box 17, Folder 168)
  - Miscellaneous, 1931-1954 (Box 17, Folder 169)
- Project Files, 1929-1956; Series III
  Series III, Project Files, consists of two sections, "Survey of Mental Health Services in Colleges," and Military and War-Related Projects.
  "Survey of Mental Health Services in Colleges" contains the data and reports of a research project conducted by psychiatrist Alice F. Raymondfrom 1940 to 1942to determine the state of psychiatric services offered in universities and colleges inthe northeastern United States. The files in this section contain reports, statistics, and related correspondence, as well as pamphlets, forms, and reports created and used by the departments being surveyed. During the survey Raymond worked for the Austen Riggs Psychiatric Foundation in Massachusetts. She came to the division in 1947 to work on military projects. Clements Collard Fry requested the unpublished survey files for departmental use. They remained in the department's files where they were presumably consulted for further publications.
  Military and War-Related Projects include the records of several National Research Council projects and those carried out by the division in concert with the Surgeon General's office and the Selective Service during and after World War II. Folders named for individuals most often contain correspondence regarding the projects on which they worked and resultant reports. Folders named for projects usually contain statistical data and financial information. Other materials include research, committee reports, and quarterly project reports tracking the division's activities, as well as supporting documentation regarding special publications the division produced on homosexuals, psychoneurotics, and psychopaths in the military. The files also contain materials documenting the military careers of former Yale student patients of the division.
  - "Survey of Mental Health Services in Colleges"
    - References, 1929-1933 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Research materials, Great Britain, 1945-1947 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Research materials, United States, 1931-1956 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Outline of survey (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Universities and colleges surveyed
      - Dartmouth College, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - Harvard University, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - Mount Holyoke College, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Simmons College, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 8)
      - University of Vermont, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - Wellesley College, 1933-1941 (Box 18, Folder 10)
      - Williams College, 1938-1941 (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - Vassar College, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 12)
      - Yale University, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Military and War-Related Projects
    - Bingham, Walter V., 1944-1945 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Bixby, Lawrence B., R.O.T.C., 1945-1947 (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - "Caught in the Draft" [newsclipping], 1944 (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - Connecticut Selective Service [inquiries from], 1943 (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - Cushing, E. H., 1943 (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - Diagnoses, undated (Box 19, Folder 19)
    - Discharges and casualties, 1945 (Box 19, Folder 20)
    - Field service report, 1943-1945 (Box 19, Folder 21)
    - Financial matters in connection with contract, 1943-1951 (Box 19, Folder 22 - 23)
    - Flying personnel research committee reports, undated (Box 19, Folder 24)
    - Fry and Rostow bibliographies [for publication], 1945 (Box 19, Folder 25)
    - Griffis, Loyd E. [Air Force], 1943-1945 (Box 19, Folder 26)
    - Harvard University, 1936-1947 (Box 19, Folder 27)
    - Hersey, Thomas F. [material given to C. C. Fry], 1943-1945 (Box 19, Folder 28)
    - Homosexuality articles [correspondence on], 1945-1952 (Box 19, Folder 29)
    - Homosexuality research project [correspondence], 1943-1946 (Box 20, Folder 30)
    - Levy Navy project outline, 1947 (Box 20, Folder 31)
    - Mobilization regulations, 1942-1945 (Box 20, Folder 32)
    - National Research Council
      - Bi-monthly reports, 1943-1945 (Box 20, Folder 33)
      - Forms and instructions, 1941-1947 (Box 20, Folder 34)
      - Research projects, 1951 (Box 20, Folder 35 - 36)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1943-1947 (Box 20, Folder 37)
    - Naval Reserve Officers' Training Corps, Perley E. Pendleton, 1947-1948 (Box 20, Folder 38)
    - "Neuropsychiatric Problems in the Army" [a report], 1945 (Box 20, Folder 39)
    - Overholser, Winfred, 1943-1945 (Box 20, Folder 40)
    - Quarterly reports to War Department, 1945-1947 (Box 20, Folder 41)
    - Regulations regarding publications, 1944-1946 (Box 20, Folder 42)
    - Rehabilitation of servicemen, 1943-1944 (Box 20, Folder 43)
    - Rejection causes, success, and subsequent performance of special groups [conference proceedings], 1948 (Box 20, Folder 44)
    - Rostow, Edna G., 1943-1944 (Box 21, Folder 45)
    - Ruggles, Arthur H., 1943-1945 (Box 21, Folder 46)
    - Selective Service
      - Rowntree, L. G., 1943-1945 (Box 21, Folder 47)
      - Release from active duty [regarding homosexuality, physical examinations] (Box 21, Folder 48)
      - "Study on Draft Board Rejects on Psychiatric Grounds," [report by John Egan] (Box 21, Folder 49)
    - Selective tests USS New Jersey, 1944 (Box 21, Folder 50)
    - Semi-annual report, 1943 (Box 21, Folder 51)
    - Statistical codes, undated (Box 21, Folder 52)
    - Stone, William S. [personality project], 1947 (Box 21, Folder 53)
    - Submarine base (New London), 1945 (Box 21, Folder 54)
    - Surgeon General's Office
      - 1943-1947 (Box 21, Folder 55)
      - 1947-1951 [Contract WD421] (Box 21, Folder 56)
    - United States Navy Department, 1943-1946 (Box 21, Folder 57)
    - United States Navy research projects, 1946-1947 (Box 21, Folder 58)
    - University of Michigan, 1943-1944 (Box 21, Folder 59)
    - War College, 1943 (Box 21, Folder 60)
    - Weed, Lewis H., 1943-1948 (Box 21, Folder 61)
    - Williams College, 1943-1945 (Box 21, Folder 62)
    - Yale patients in service [project proposal], 1943 (Box 21, Folder 63)
      See also: Series III. Project Files, 1929-1956 Folder 53 See also: Series III. Project Files, 1929-1956 Folder 44 See also: Series III. Project Files, 1929-1956 Folder 31 See also: Series III. Project Files, 1929-1956 Folder 27
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1943-1948 (Box 21, Folder 64)
- Financial Records, 1949-1969
  Restricted materials contain the month by month payroll records from 1949 to 1969, citing names, amounts of pay, and from which budget line the salary was drawn. The files represent the only record of individuals employed by the division.
  Conditions Governing Access
  These records are closed until January 1, 2044.
  - Budget, 1950-1960 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Old Dominion Fund Payroll Records, 1949-1969 (Box 22, Folder 2 - 3)